Ngũgĩ mss., ca. 1950s-2014 LMC 2905
Lilly Library
Ngũgĩ mss.
ca. 1950s-2014
Lilly Library
Ngũgĩ wa Thiong'o
LMC 2905
79 Boxes 74 standard, 5 custom
The Ngũgĩ mss. (ca. 1950s-2014) consist of the papers of Kenyan author, playwright, essayist, educator, and activist Ngũgĩ wa Thiong'o.
Access Restrictions
This collection is open for research.
Many collections are housed offsite; retrieval requires advance notice. Please make an appointment a minimum of one week in advance of your visit.
Biographical Note
The Ngũgĩ mss. (ca. 1950s-2014) consist of the papers of Kenyan author, playwright, essayist, educator, and activist Ngũgĩ wa Thiong'o. Born in Limuru, Kenya, on January 5, 1938, Ngũgĩ was raised a Christian and attended Church of Scotland Mission school at Kamaandura. Eventually he attended a Gĩkũyũ independent school, and later Alliance High School. He went on to attend Makerere University College, Kampala, Uganda, and the University of Leeds, Britain. Both British colonialism (which ended in 1963 ) and the Mau Mau Rebellion had a profound impact on him, and each is reflected in his non-fiction writings and creative works.
Ngũgĩ burst onto the theatrical and literary scenes with his acclaimed debut play, The Black Hermit ( 1963 ), and his successful first novel, Weep Not, Child ( 1964 ). He cemented his reputation with a pair of subsequent novels: The River Between ( 1965 ) and A Grain of Wheat ( 1967 ). Years later, he caused a stir with The Trial of Dedan Kimathi ( 1976 ) a stage production about the Mau Mau Rebellion. Ngũgĩ's novel Petals of Blood and play Ngaahika Ndeenda (aka I Will Marry When I Want), both 1977, were openly critical of life in neo-colonial Kenya and precipitated his imprisonment from December 31, 1977 to December 12, 1978. (He never was formally charged with a crime.) Ngũgĩ found employment difficult following his release and eventually fled into exile in 1982. That same year he published Detained: A Writer's Prison Diary, an account of his incarceration, and Devil on the Cross, which he surreptitiously wrote in on a roll of toilet paper in his native Gĩkũyũ (the first modern novel in that language) while imprisoned. His later works include two novels, Matigari ( 1989 ) and The Wizard of the Crow ( 2006 ), and two memoirs, Dreams in a Time of War and In the House of the Interpreter ( 2012 ). He has taught and lectured at several universities in the United Kingdom and United States, most recently at the University of California, Irvine, and has received numerous honorary doctorates and literary awards.
Scope and Content Note
Writings include original drafts of all of Ngũgĩ's significant works, many in both English (or English translation) and Gĩkũyũ. Included as well are screenplays and other materials pertaining to a documentary about the Senegalese filmmaker Ousmane Sembène, co-directed by Ngũgĩ. Approximately five decades of correspondence, primarily with friends, colleagues, and publishers, are also featured, with letters pertaining to (and in protest of) Ngũgĩ's 1977-1978 incarceration of particular interest.
Acquisition Information
Acquired: 2016
Arrangement
This collection is arranged into the following series: I. Correspondence, II. Writings by Ngũgĩ, III. Writings by Others, IV. Mũtiiri, V. Imprisonment, VI. Activism, VII. Education, VIII. Conferences, IX. Interviews, X. Theatre, XI. Film, XII. Subject Files, XIII. Travel, XIV. Ephemera, XV. Photos, XVI. Personal/Family, XVII. Clippings, XVIII. Research, XIX. Printed Material, XX. Legal, XXI. Financial, XXII. Address books, XXIII. Notebooks, XXIV. Audio Visual and Born Digital, XXV. Awards, Certificates, Degrees, XXVI. Posters, Broadsides, and XXVII. Miscellaneous.
XVII. Clippings consists of newspaper and magazine clippings about Ngũgĩ. XVIII. Research consists of photocopies of copyrighted materials that may have been used as handouts for teaching and other scholarly materials. XIX. Printed material consists mainly of magazines and other mass produced, copyrighted printed material. XX. Legal includes Ngũgĩ's I-485 applications for permanent residence in the United States, court documents related to some civil cases, and contracts and agreements for many of Ngũgĩ's works. XXI. Financial includes royalty statements and various receipts, invoices, and bills.
Authors, African--Correspondence; Political activists -- Africa; Educators -- Africa; Decolonization -- Africa; Ngũgĩ wa Thiong'o, 1938-; Ngũgĩ wa Thiong'o, 1938---Correspondence
- I. Correspondence
  - January 1961-July 1963 (Box 1)
  - August 1963-February 1967 (Box 1)
  - March 1967-December 1969 (Box 1)
  - Makerere Writers Workshop, 1970 (Box 1)
  - January 1970-October 1970 (Box 1)
  - November 1970-April 1971 (Box 1)
  - May 1971-December1971 (Box 1)
  - January 1972-December 1973 (Box 1)
  - January 1974-December 1974 (Box 1)
  - January 1975-June 1975 (Box 1)
  - July 1975 - December 1975 (Box 1)
  - January 1976-June 1976 (Box 1)
  - July 1976-December 1976 (Box 1)
  - January 1977-May 1977 (Box 1)
  - June 1977-September 1977 (Box 1)
  - October 1977-December 1977 (Box 1)
  - 1978 (Box 1)
  - Prison Correspondence (2 folders), 1978 (Box 1)
  - January 1979-June 1979 (Box 1)
  - July 1979-December 1979 (Box 1)
  - January 1980-July 1980 (Box 1)
  - August 1980-December 1980 (Box 1)
  - January 1981-September 1981 (Box 2)
  - October 1981-December 1981 (Box 2)
  - Sweeden and Denmark Visit, 1982 (Box 2)
  - January 1982-May 1982 (Box 2)
  - June 1982-April 1983 (Box 2)
  - May 1983-June 1983 (Box 2)
  - July 1983-October 1983 (Box 2)
  - September 1983-December 1984 (Box 2)
  - 1985 (Box 2)
  - 1986 (Box 2)
  - 1987 (Box 2)
  - 1988 (Box 2)
  - January 1989-June 1989 (Box 2)
  - July 1989-December 1989 (Box 2)
  - January 1990-October 1990 (Box 2)
  - 1991 (Box 2)
  - 1992 (Box 2)
  - January 1993-June 1993 (Box 2)
  - July 1993-December 1993 (Box 2)
  - January 1994-March 1994 (Box 3)
  - April 1994-July 1994 (Box 3)
  - August 1994-February 1995 (Box 3)
  - March 1995-July 1995 (Box 3)
  - August 1995-December 1995 (Box 3)
  - January 1996-April 1996 (Box 3)
  - May 1996-December 1996 (Box 3)
  - 1997 (Box 3)
  - 1998 (Box 3)
  - 1999 (Box 3)
  - 2000-2001 (Box 3)
  - 2002-2009 (Box 3)
  - Paul Chinnock (Box 3)
  - Undated (2 folders) (Box 3)
- II. Writings by Ngũgĩ
  - Early Writings
    - Diaries (Box 3)
      - Diary, 1961-1964 (Box 3)
      - Diary, 1966 (Box 3)
    - School Papers
      - Class notes, notebooks - handwritten (3 folders), undated (Box 3)
      - Class papers - handwritten (3 folders), undated (Box 4)
      - "Anna Karenina" - typescript, undated (Box 4)
      - "A Colonial Affair" - typescript (first page only), undated (Box 4)
      - "Challenge of the Congo, by Kwame Nkrumah, a review" - typescript, undated, July 1967 (Box 4)
      - "Expectations: A View of England" - typescript, undated (Box 4)
      - "The Past as Reflected in West Indian Literature" - annotated typescript, undated (Ngũgĩ?) (Box 4)
      - "Politics and the Novel" - handwritten, undated (Box 4)
      - "The Significance of the Secret Sharer" - photocopy of typescript, undated (Box 4)
      - "The Theme of Exile in the West Indian Novel" (Box 4)
        - Draft - handwritten, undated (Box 4)
        - Draft - annotated typescript, undated (Box 4)
        - Draft - typescript, undated (Box 4)
        - Draft - typescript, undated (Box 4)
        - Draft - typescript, undated (Box 4)
      - "Why Nostromo" - photocopy of handwritten paper, January 26, 1964 (Box 4)
    - Short Stories
      - "And the Rain Came Down" (Box 4)
        - Early draft - handwritten, undated (Box 4)
        - Draft - handwritten, undated (Box 4)
      - "The Black Bird" (Box 4)
        - Draft - handwritten, undated (Box 4)
        - Draft - typescript, undated (Box 4)
        - Annotated print copy, undated (Box 4)
      - "Childhood Memories" - draft, handwritten, undated (Box 4)
      - "Disintegration!" - draft, handwritten, undated (Box 4)
      - "The Fig Tree" - annotated typescript, undated (Box 4)
      - "Gone with the Drought" (Box 4)
        - Early draft - handwritten, titled "The Drought", undated (Box 4)
        - Early draft - handwritten, titled "The Drought and the Woman", undated (Box 4)
      - "Home-Coming" - draft, handwritten, undated (Box 4)
      - "The House" - draft, handwritten, undated (Box 4)
      - "The Housemaid" - annotated typescript, undated (Ngũgĩ?) (Box 4)
      - "The Man Who Feared a Crowd!" - draft, handwritten, undated (Box 4)
      - "The Martyr!" (Box 4)
        - Typescript, undated (Box 4)
        - Annotated print copy, undated (Box 4)
      - "Mine Brother" - draft, handwritten, undated (Box 4)
      - "The Mubenzi Tribesman" - early draft, titled "Turn to the Light", handwritten, undated (Box 4)
      - "Mugumo-ini (Under the Sacred Fig Tree)" - draft, handwritten, undated (Box 4)
      - "My Grandmother" - drafts, handwritten (2 folders), undated (Box 4)
      - "The Return" - print copy, Pen no.11, October 1961 (Box 4)
      - "The Village Priest" - draft, handwritten, undated (Box 4)
      - "The Wind" - draft, handwritten, undated (Box 4)
      - Notepad, handwritten, containing multiple early drafts (The Black Bird, The Village Priest), undated (Box 4)
      - Unidentified - handwritten on loose notebook papers (4 folders), undated (Box 4)
  - Novels
    - Weep Not, Child
      - Outline - handwritten, undated (Box 4)
      - Early draft - handwritten, undated (Box 4)
      - Draft - handwritten notebook, February 28, 1962 (Box 4)
    - The River Between
      - Early draft - handwritten, undated (Box 4)
      - Draft - handwritten, undated (Box 4)
      - Draft - annotated typescript, undated (Box 4)
      - Draft - typescript (Box 4)
      - Printer's pages - 5 pages, undated (Box 4)
    - A Grain of Wheat
      - Early draft - handwritten, 1961/1962? (Box 4)
      - Early draft - handwritten, titled "Wrestling with God", undated (Box 4)
      - First draft - hand written notebooks (3 folders), undated (Box 4)
      - Third draft - handwritten and typescript (2 folders), undated (Box 5)
      - Draft - typescript, (2 folders), 1965 (Box 5)
    - Petals of Blood
      - Draft - annotated typescript (2 folders), October 1970 - October 1975 (Box 5)
      - Draft - annotated typescript (2 folders), undated (Box 5)
      - Draft - handwritten (3 folders), undated (Box 5)
      - Incomplete drafts - handwritten and typescript (19 folders), undated (Box 5, Box 6)
    - Devil on the Cross (Caitaani mutharaba-Ini)
      - Draft - handwritten on prison issued toilet paper, 1977-1978 (Box 75)
      - Draft - annotated typescript in Gĩkũyũ (3 folders), undated (Box 6)
      - Draft - annotated typescript in Gĩkũyũ (3 folders), undated (Box 6)
      - Draft - annotated typescript in Gĩkũyũ (3 folders), undated (Box 6)
      - Incomplete drafts - handwritten in Gĩkũyũ (3 folders), undated (Box 7)
      - Draft - handwritten (3 folders), undated (Box 7)
      - Incomplete drafts - handwritten (3 folders), undated (Box 7)
      - Setting pages - 5 pages, undated (Box 7)
      - Reader's Report, undated (Box 7)
    - Matigari (Matigari ma Njirrngi)
      - Draft - handwritten in Gĩkũyũ (2 folders), undated (Box 7)
      - Draft - handwritten and annotated typescript in Gĩkũyũ, (3 folders), January 14, 1985 (Box 7)
      - Draft - annotated typescript (2 folders), undated (Box 7)
      - Draft - annotated typescript, (2 folders), undated (Box 7)
    - Wizard of the Crow (Mũrogi wa Kagogo)
      - Incomplete drafts - typescripts in Gĩkũyũ (16 folders), undated (Box 7, Box 8)
      - Draft - typescript (13 folders), undated (Box 8, Box 9)
      - Draft - typescript (14 folders), undated (Box 9, Box 10)
      - Copy edited draft (7 folders), undated (Box 9)
      - Rough pages (5 folders), November 9, 2005 (Box 10)
      - Incomplete drafts - typescripts (9 folders), undated (Box 11)
      - For Henry Chakava: Mũrogi wa Kagogo (Box 11)
    - Bound drafts - typescripts, undated (Box 12, Box 13, Box 14)
    - Bound drafts - typescripts in Gĩkũyũ, undated (Box 15, Box 16, Box 17, Box 18, Box 19, Box 20)
  - Short Story Collections
    - Secret Lives and Other Stories
      - Book cover, undated (Box 21)
      - Drafts - handwritten and annotated typescripts of multiple short stories (3 folders) (Box 21)
      - "Secret Lives: Another Word" (Box 21)
        - Draft - handwritten, undated (Box 21)
        - Draft - annotated typescript, undated (Box 21)
        - Draft - typescript, undated (Box 21)
  - Plays
    - The Black Hermit
      - Draft - annotated typescript, November 1962 (Box 21)
      - Draft - notebook containing handwritten and annotated typescript with stage directions, undated (Box 21)
      - Draft - handwritten notebook, March 1966 (Box 21)
      - Draft - annotated typescript (preface only), March 1966 (Box 21)
      - Draft - annotated typescript, May 1967 (Box 21)
    - This Time Tomorrow
      - Early draft - handwritten, titled "Harambee", undated (Box 21)
      - Draft - annotated typescript, undated (Box 21)
      - Draft - annotated typescript, undated (Box 21)
      - Draft - typescript, undated (Box 21)
      - The Rebels (Box 21)
        - Draft - handwritten outline, undated (Box 21)
        - Draft - typescript, undated (Box 21)
    - The Trial of Dedan Kimathi
      - Early draft - handwritten, undated (Box 21)
      - Draft - handwritten and annotated typescript, undated (Box 21)
      - Draft - annotated typescript, undated (Box 21)
      - Draft - annotated typescript, undated (Box 21)
      - Draft - typescript, undated (Box 21)
      - Incomplete drafts - handwritten, undated (Box 21)
      - Draft - typescript in Gĩkũyũ, undated (Box 21)
    - Ngaahika Ndeenda (I Will Marry When I Want)
      - Draft - annotated photocopy of handwritten pages in Gĩkũyũ, undated (Box 21)
      - Incomplete drafts - handwritten and typescript in Gĩkũyũ (3 folders), undated (Box 21)
      - Book cover - African Writer's Series, undated (Box 21)
      - Draft - handwritten, undated (Box 21)
      - Swahili translation - bound typescript, undated (Box 21)
    - Maitũ Njugĩra (Mother, Sing for Me)
      - Draft - handwritten in Gĩkũyũ, November 5, 1981 (Box 22)
      - Draft - photocopy of handwritten pages in Gĩkũyũ, undated (Box 22)
      - Draft - annotated typescript in Gĩkũyũ, undated (Box 22)
      - Draft - annotated typescript in Gĩkũyũ, undated (Box 22)
      - Draft - annotated typescript in Gĩkũyũ, undated (Box 22)
      - Draft - annotated typescript in Gĩkũyũ, undated (Box 22)
      - Draft - typescript in Gĩkũyũ, undated (Box 22)
      - Typescript in Gĩkũyũ, undated (Box 22)
      - Typescript in Gĩkũyũ, undated (Box 22)
      - Song drafts - handwritten in Gĩkũyũ, undated (Box 22)
      - Incomplete drafts - handwritten and annotated typescripts in Gĩkũyũ (2 folders), undated (Box 22)
      - Annotated transcript, undated (Box 22)
      - Photocopy of annotated transcript, undated (Box 22)
      - Photocopy of annotated transcript, undated (Box 22)
      - Incomplete draft - typescript, undated (Box 22)
      - Stage directions (Box 22)
      - "The Language Issue" - handwritten, undated (Box 22)
  - Film
    - Maitũ Njugĩra (Mother, Sing for Me)
      - Outline - handwritten notebook, undated (Box 22)
      - Outline and notes - handwritten notebook, undated (Box 22)
      - Screnplay - handwritten, undated (Box 23)
      - Summary - photocopy of handwritten pages, undated (Box 23)
      - Film script - annotated typescript, bound, undated (Box 23)
      - Film script - annotated typescript, bound, undated (Box 23)
      - Film script - annotated typescript, titled "The Plantation", undated (Box 23)
      - Film script - typescript, titled "The Plantation", undated (Box 23)
      - Film script - typescript, titled "The Plantation", undated (Box 23)
      - Film script - typescript, titled "The Plantation", undated (Box 23)
      - Film Script - annotated typescript titled "Kariũki", January 1989 (Box 23)
    - Africa in Sweden
      - Film script - handwritten, 1986 (Box 23)
    - Blodsdruvor och Svarta Diamenter (Blood grapes and Black Diamonds)
      - Film script - annotated typescript, February 1986 (Box 23)
  - Memoirs
    - Detained: A Writer's Prison Diary
      - Draft - handwritten (2 folders), undated (Box 23)
      - Draft - handwritten (2 folders), 1980 (Box 23)
      - Incomplete draft - handwritten, undated (Box 23)
    - Dreams in a Time of War
      - Draft - annotated typescript (2 folders), February 12, 2009 (Box 23)
      - Rough proof (2 folders), October 20, 2009 (Box 23)
    - In the House of the Interpreter: A Memoir
      - Proofs (2 folders), June 8, 2012 (Box 23)
      - Proofs (2 folders), July 27, 2012 (Box 23)
      - Proofs (2 folders), August 23, 2012 (Box 23, Box 24)
      - Setting copy (2 folders) (Box 24)
    - My Life {1938-1954}
      - Draft - typescript (2 folders), August 4, 2008 (Box 24)
  - Children's Stories
    - Njamba Nene
      - Background - photocopy of typescript, undated (Box 24)
      - Draft - handwritten notebook, undated (Box 24)
      - Draft - handwritten, undated (Box 24)
      - Njamba Nene na Mbaathi ĩ Mathagu (Njamba Nene and the Flying Bus) (Box 24)
        - Draft - handwritten, undated (Box 24)
        - Draft - handwritten, undated (Box 24)
        - Typescript, undated (Box 24)
        - Typescript, undated (Box 24)
        - Photocopy of annotated transcript, undated (Box 24)
      - Njamba Nene na Chibu King'ang'I (Njamba Nene and the Cruel Chief) (Box 24)
        - Draft - handwritten with annotations, undated (Box 24)
        - Draft - handwritten, undated (Box 24)
        - Typescript, undated (Box 24)
      - Bathitoora ya Njamba Nene (Njamba Nene's Pistol) (Box 24)
        - Draft - handwritten, undated (Box 24)
        - Draft - handwritten, undated (Box 24)
        - Typescript, undated (Box 24)
        - Typescript, undated (Box 24)
    - The Upright Revolution: Or Why Human's Walk Upright - typescript in English and Gĩkũyũ, 20012 (Box 24)
  - Non-Fiction
    - Something Torn and New: An African Renaissance - proof, November 5, 2008 (Box 24)
    - Globalectics: Theory and the Politics of Knowing - proof, August 24, 2011 (Box 24)
    - In the Name of the Mother: Reflections on Writers and Empire (Box 24)
      - Proofs and index, May 6, 2013 (Box 24)
      - Copy edited manuscript, June 12, 2013 (Box 24)
  - Poetry
    - "Petals of Love" - Draft, handwritten, Yalta, September 16, 1975 (Box 24)
  - Essays
    - "After Asmara: The Future of Literature and Scholarship in Africa" - annotated typescript, undated (Box 24)
    - "And Then Came Okot p'Bitek: Notes on East African Writing" - handwritten, undated (Box 24)
    - "An Appeal to All Writer's Organizations" - handwritten, April 24, 1983 (Box 24)
    - "Art War with the State: The Writers and Politics of Contemporary Africa" - typescript, undated (Box 24)
    - "The Asmara Declaration of African Languages and Literatures" - typescript, January 17, 2000 (Box 24)
    - "A Call for Action" typescript, undated (Box 24)
    - "Chinua Achebe: A Man of the People" (Box 24)
      - Draft - annotated typescript, undated (Box 24)
      - Typescript, undated (Box 24)
    - "Church, Culture, and Politics" (Box 24)
      - Draft - handwritten, titled " The Role of the Church Today", undated (Box 24)
      - Draft - handwritten, titled " The Role of the Church in Kenya Today", undated (Box 24)
      - Draft - annotated typescript, undated (Box 24)
      - Typescript, undated (Box 24)
    - "Civilization: A Comment" - handwritten, undated (Box 24)
    - "Colonialism, Patriarchy and Gender Politics: Dangarembga's Nervous Condition" - typescript, undated (Box 24)
    - "Comments on the 92 Multi-Party Elections in Kenya" - typescript, undated, December 30, 1992 (Box 24)
    - "The Crisis of Culture in Africa" - typescript, undated (Box 24)
    - "Culture, Democracy, and the Challenge of Sustainable Development in the Nineties" - annotated typescript, undated (Box 24)
    - "Decolonizing the Means of Imagination" (Box 24)
      - Typescript, undated (Box 24)
      - Annotated typescript, undated (Box 24)
    - "Decolonizing the Mind: The Politics of Language in African Literature" (Box 24)
      - Photocopy of annotated transcript, undated (Box 24)
      - "The Quest for Relevance" - draft, handwritten, undated (Box 24)
      - Mali translation - first draft, bound, 2009 (Box 24)
    - "Emergency International Conference on Korea (a report)" (Box 24)
      - Draft - handwritten, undated (Box 24)
      - Draft - handwritten, undated (Box 24)
    - "Encounters with Censorship" - typescript, undated (Box 24)
    - "Europhonism, Universities, and the Magic Fountain: The Future of African Literature and Scholarship" (Box 25)
      - Print copy, Spring 2000 (Box 25)
      - Annotated typescript, undated (Box 25)
    - "Father of Apples" - Draft, handwritten, undated (Box 25)
    - "Finding Our Way in the World" - typescript, undated (Box 25)
    - "Freedom of the Artist" (Box 25)
      - Draft - handwritten, undated (Box 25)
      - Draft - annotated typescript, undated (Box 25)
      - Annotated typescript, undated (Box 25)
      - Annotated typescript, undated (Box 25)
      - Annotated typescript, undated (Box 25)
    - "George Lamming and the Colonial Situation" - typescript, undated (Box 25)
    - "George Lamming: In the Castle of My Skin" (Box 25)
      - Draft - handwritten, (first page), undated (Box 25)
      - Draft - annotated typescript, undated (Box 25)
      - Typescript, undated (Box 25)
    - "The Interpreters" - annotated typescript, undated (Box 25)
    - "J.M.: A Writer's Tribute" - annotated typescript, March 24, 1975 (Box 25)
    - "Kenya: The Challenge for Independence" - draft, handwritten, undated (Box 25)
    - "Kenyan Culture: The Choice Before Us!" - handwritten, undated (Box 25)
    - "The Kenyan Woman: A Decade of Oppression" (Box 25)
      - Draft - handwritten, undated (Box 25)
      - Draft - handwritten, undated (Box 25)
      - Draft - handwritten, undated (Box 25)
      - Annotated typescript, undated (Box 25)
    - "A Kind of Homecoming" (Box 25)
      - Draft - handwritten, undated (Box 25)
      - Draft - annotated typescript, undated (Box 25)
      - Draft - annotated typescript, undated (Box 25)
    - "Kũũngũ Baaba Mandela! (Welcome Home Baba Mandela!)" (Box 25)
      - Draft - annotated typescript in Gĩkũyũ, February 8, 1990 (Box 25)
      - Draft - photocopies of annotated typescript, February 10, 1990 (Box 25)
    - "Learning from the South" (Box 25)
      - Draft - handwritten, undated (Box 25)
      - Draft - annotated typescript (Box 25)
    - "Literature in Schools" - draft, handwritten, undated (Box 25)
    - "March is a momentous month for the Kenyan people" - draft, handwritten, undated (Box 25)
    - "Mau Mau is Coming Back: The Revolutionary Significance of 20th October 1952 in Kenya Today " (Box 25)
      - Draft - handwritten (Box 25)
      - Typescript, October 22, 1922 (Box 25)
    - "Mau Mau: A Cultural Assertation" (Box 25)
      - Draft - handwritten, undated (Box 25)
      - Draft - annotated typescript, undated (Box 25)
    - "Mau Mau Detained" (Box 25)
      - Draft - handwritten, undated (Box 25)
      - Draft - handwritten, undated (Box 25)
    - "Mau Mau and Neo - Colonialism in Kenya" - draft, handwritten and annotated typescript, 1986 (Box 25)
    - "Mau Mau Unchained" - annotated print copy, undated (Box 25)
    - "Mau Mau, Violence, and Culture" - annotated typescript, undated (Box 25)
    - "Moving the Center: Move Africa into the Circle" - annotated typescript, undated (Box 25)
    - "Moving the Center: The Struggle for Cultural Freedoms" (Box 25)
      - Proofs, undated (Box 25)
      - Preface, draft, undated (Box 25)